<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6234 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6234.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6962 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6962.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8610 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8610.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8949.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC9052 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9052.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC9334 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9334.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.condrey-rats-pop SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.condrey-rats-pop.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" submissionType="independent"
     docName="draft-condrey-rats-pop-aggregation-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="PoP Aggregation">Proof of Process: Succinct Evidence Aggregation Extension</title>

    <author fullname="David Condrey" initials="D." surname="Condrey">
      <organization>Writerslogic Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>david@writerslogic.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" day="6" year="2026"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Remote ATtestation procedureS</workgroup>

    <keyword>VDF</keyword>
    <keyword>aggregation</keyword>
    <keyword>STARK</keyword>
    <keyword>Halo2</keyword>
    <keyword>Succinct Evidence</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines an extension to the Proof of Process
      architecture that enables succinct aggregation of evidence records
      using Merkle tree structures and recursive proof systems.  By
      leveraging Verifiable Delay Functions (VDFs), STARK proof
      composition, and Halo2 recursive circuits, Verifiers can
      efficiently validate large volumes of authorship evidence without
      processing each individual record.  The aggregation mechanism
      preserves the temporal ordering guarantees of the base protocol
      while reducing verification complexity from linear to
      logarithmic.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Proof of Process (PoP) architecture defined in the base
      specification generates a continuous stream of evidence records
      during the creative authorship process.  For long-duration works
      or prolific authors, the volume of evidence can grow to millions
      of individual records, making full verification impractical for
      many Relying Parties.</t>

      <t>This document specifies a succinct aggregation extension that
      compresses arbitrarily large evidence chains into constant-size
      proofs.  The extension operates at three levels: Merkle tree
      commitment of batched VDF outputs, STARK-based proof composition
      for cross-batch verification, and Halo2 recursive circuits for
      full-chain summarization.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
      RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
      interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
      all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Merkle Tree Aggregation">
      <t>Evidence records produced during a single authorship session
      are organized into a binary Merkle tree as defined in
      <xref target="RFC6962"/>.  Each leaf node contains the SHA-256
      hash (<xref target="RFC6234"/>) of a serialized evidence record
      encoded in CBOR (<xref target="RFC8949"/>).  The Merkle root
      serves as a succinct commitment to the entire batch.</t>

      <t>The Attester MUST construct the Merkle tree using the
      append-only property: new evidence records are added as
      rightmost leaves, and the tree is never rebalanced.  This
      ensures that inclusion proofs for earlier records remain valid
      as new records are appended.  Batch sizes SHOULD be powers of
      two to simplify proof generation.</t>

      <t>Inclusion proofs allow a Verifier to confirm that a specific
      evidence record is part of a committed batch without downloading
      the entire batch.  The proof consists of the sibling hashes
      along the path from the leaf to the root, requiring O(log n)
      hashes for a batch of n records.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Recursive Proof Composition">
      <t>While Merkle trees provide efficient inclusion proofs within
      a single batch, verifying temporal ordering across batches still
      requires processing each batch root sequentially.  This document
      defines a recursive proof composition scheme using STARK and
      Halo2 proof systems to eliminate this linear dependency.</t>

      <t>A STARK proof attests to the correct computation of VDF
      outputs within a batch.  The prover generates a STARK proof
      that the VDF chain from the first to the last record in a batch
      was computed correctly.  Multiple STARK proofs are then composed
      using Halo2 recursive circuits, producing a single constant-size
      proof that covers an arbitrary number of batches.</t>

      <t>The recursive proof MUST be signed using COSE_Sign1
      (<xref target="RFC9052"/>) with the same Attester key used for
      individual evidence records.  The payload of the COSE structure
      contains the Halo2 proof bytes, the first and last VDF outputs,
      and the total record count.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The aggregation mechanism introduces a trust dependency on
      the soundness of the underlying proof systems.  If the STARK or
      Halo2 proof system is broken, an adversary could forge aggregated
      proofs without possessing the original evidence.  Implementers
      SHOULD support multiple proof systems to allow migration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC6234;
      &RFC6962;
      &RFC8610;
      &RFC8949;
      &RFC9052;
      &I-D.condrey-rats-pop;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC9334;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
