<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8949.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC9052 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9052.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC9334 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9334.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6960 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6960.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.condrey-rats-pop SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.condrey-rats-pop.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-condrey-rats-witnessd-revocation-01" category="std" consensus="true" submissionType="independent">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="PoP Revocation">Evidence Status and Revocation Protocol for Proof of Process</title>

    <author fullname="David Condrey" initials="D." surname="Condrey">
      <organization>Writerslogic Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>david@writerslogic.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" day="6" year="2026"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Remote ATtestation procedureS</workgroup>

    <keyword>attestation</keyword>
    <keyword>revocation</keyword>
    <keyword>privacy</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the evidence status and revocation
      protocol for the Proof of Process architecture.  It specifies
      mechanisms for revoking compromised evidence chains, checking
      the validity status of previously issued attestation results,
      and revoking device attestation certificates when Attester
      keys are compromised.  The protocol balances the need for
      timely revocation with author privacy by using privacy-
      preserving status checking that does not reveal which specific
      evidence chains are being queried.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Proof of Process architecture generates long-lived
      evidence chains and attestation results that Relying Parties
      may depend on months or years after their creation.  Over such
      time spans, the security assumptions underlying the evidence
      may change: device keys may be compromised, software
      vulnerabilities may be discovered in Attester implementations,
      or authors may discover that evidence was collected during
      periods of unauthorized access to their devices.</t>

      <t>This document defines a revocation and status checking
      protocol that allows evidence chains and device certificates
      to be revoked, and that allows Relying Parties to check the
      current validity of evidence they depend on.  The protocol
      draws on established revocation mechanisms from the PKI
      ecosystem (<xref target="RFC5280"/>, <xref target="RFC6960"/>)
      while adapting them to the specific requirements of the Proof
      of Process architecture.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
      RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
      interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
      all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Evidence Revocation">
      <t>An author MAY revoke a specific evidence chain or a range
      of evidence records within a chain.  Revocation is performed
      by submitting a signed revocation request to the status service.
      The revocation request MUST be signed with the same device key
      that produced the original evidence, or with a designated
      revocation key established during enrollment.</t>

      <t>The revocation request contains the evidence chain
      identifier, the range of sequence numbers to revoke (or a
      wildcard indicating the entire chain), a revocation reason
      code, and an optional revocation timestamp.  Valid reason
      codes include key compromise, software vulnerability,
      unauthorized access, and voluntary withdrawal.  The request
      is encoded in CBOR (<xref target="RFC8949"/>) and wrapped
      in a COSE_Sign1 structure (<xref target="RFC9052"/>).</t>

      <t>Once a revocation request is accepted, the status service
      MUST include the revoked evidence in all subsequent status
      responses.  Revocation is permanent and cannot be reversed.
      If an author wishes to re-establish evidence for a work
      whose chain was revoked, they MUST create a new evidence
      chain from the current document state.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Status Checking Protocol">
      <t>Relying Parties check the validity of evidence chains and
      device certificates using a status checking protocol inspired
      by OCSP (<xref target="RFC6960"/>).  The Relying Party sends
      a status request containing the hash of the evidence chain
      identifier to the status service.  The service responds with
      a signed status response indicating whether the evidence is
      valid, revoked, or unknown.</t>

      <t>To protect author privacy, the status checking protocol
      uses a blinded query mechanism.  The Relying Party computes a
      blinded hash of the evidence chain identifier and sends this
      blinded value to the status service.  The service evaluates
      the query against its revocation database without learning
      which specific evidence chain is being checked.  This prevents
      the status service from building a profile of which evidence
      chains are most frequently queried.</t>

      <t>Status responses are signed by the status service key and
      include a freshness timestamp and a next-update time.  Relying
      Parties SHOULD cache status responses until the next-update
      time to reduce query frequency.  A cached response that has
      passed its next-update time MUST be refreshed before the
      Relying Party makes any new trust decisions based on the
      corresponding evidence.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Device Certificate Revocation">
      <t>Device attestation certificates issued during enrollment
      may need to be revoked if the Attester's private key is
      compromised.  Certificate revocation follows the standard
      X.509 revocation model (<xref target="RFC5280"/>), with the
      Endorser publishing Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs) at
      regular intervals.  Verifiers MUST check the revocation status
      of the device certificate before accepting evidence signed by
      the corresponding key as described in the RATS architecture
      (<xref target="RFC9334"/>).</t>

      <t>When a device certificate is revoked, all evidence produced
      by that device after the revocation effective date is
      automatically considered invalid.  Evidence produced before
      the revocation effective date remains valid unless separately
      revoked through the evidence revocation mechanism described
      above.  This distinction allows Relying Parties to continue
      trusting historical evidence from a device whose key was
      compromised at a known point in time.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The revocation protocol introduces a dependency on the
      availability of the status service.  If the status service is
      unreachable, Relying Parties must decide whether to accept
      evidence without a fresh status check (fail-open) or reject
      it (fail-closed).  This document RECOMMENDS a fail-closed
      policy for high-value evidence, such as evidence used in
      legal proceedings, and permits fail-open with cached responses
      for lower-stakes applications.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC8949;
      &RFC9052;
      &RFC5280;
      &RFC6960;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC9334;
      &I-D.condrey-rats-pop;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
