<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC8949 SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8949.xml">
  <!ENTITY I-D.condrey-rats-pop SYSTEM "https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.condrey-rats-pop.xml">
]>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" submissionType="independent"
     docName="draft-condrey-rats-pop-examples-01">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="PoP Examples">Proof of Process: Worked Examples</title>

    <author fullname="David Condrey" initials="D." surname="Condrey">
      <organization>Writerslogic Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>david@writerslogic.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" day="6" year="2026"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Remote ATtestation procedureS</workgroup>

    <keyword>attestation</keyword>
    <keyword>evidence</keyword>
    <keyword>authorship</keyword>
    <keyword>examples</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides step-by-step worked examples of
      evidence collection, chain construction, and verification
      using the Proof of Process architecture.  The examples
      illustrate typical authorship scenarios including a short
      writing session, a multi-day project, and a verification
      workflow.  Each example includes representative data values
      to assist implementers in testing their systems.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Proof of Process (PoP) specification defines the
      architecture and data formats for authorship attestation,
      but the abstract protocol description can be difficult to
      follow without concrete examples.  This companion document
      walks through several representative scenarios, showing the
      exact sequence of operations performed by the Attester,
      the data structures produced, and the verification steps
      carried out by the Verifier.</t>

      <t>All examples in this document use simplified values for
      readability.  Hash values are truncated, timestamps are
      shown in human-readable form, and VDF outputs are represented
      as short hexadecimal strings.  Production implementations
      will use full-length values as specified in the base
      protocol.</t>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
      "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
      RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
      interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
      <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
      all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example 1: Short Writing Session">
      <t>Alice begins writing a 500-word blog post at 10:00 AM.  Her
      Attester device generates a session initialization record
      containing a fresh VDF seed derived from hardware entropy.  The
      session record is signed with Alice's device key and stored
      locally.</t>

      <t>Over the next 25 minutes, the Attester captures evidence at
      30-second intervals.  Each evidence packet includes the
      keystroke timing deltas since the previous packet, the SHA-256
      hash of the current document state, and a VDF output computed
      from the previous packet's VDF output concatenated with the
      current content hash.  By 10:25 AM, the chain contains 50
      evidence records.</t>

      <t>Alice finishes the blog post and closes her editor.  The
      Attester produces a session finalization record that includes
      the final document hash, the total word count (512 words), and
      the cumulative VDF output.  The complete evidence chain is
      serialized in CBOR (<xref target="RFC8949"/>) and stored
      alongside the finished document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example 2: Multi-Day Project">
      <t>Bob is writing a 10,000-word short story over five days.
      Each day, he opens the document and the Attester resumes the
      evidence chain from where it left off.  The session resumption
      record references the last evidence packet from the previous
      session, ensuring chain continuity across editing sessions.</t>

      <t>On day three, Bob takes a two-hour break in the middle of
      a session.  The Attester detects the period of inactivity and
      produces an idle marker record.  When Bob resumes typing, the
      Attester generates a resumption record that includes both a
      fresh VDF computation and a reference to the idle marker.  This
      gap handling ensures that the evidence chain accurately reflects
      the actual timeline of creative effort.</t>

      <t>By the end of day five, Bob's evidence chain contains 1,247
      records spanning 14 hours of active writing time.  The chain
      captures the evolution of the story from a 200-word outline to
      the final 10,340-word manuscript, providing a complete temporal
      record of the authorship process.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Example 3: Verification Workflow">
      <t>Carol is a literary agent who has received Bob's manuscript
      along with the exported evidence chain.  She submits the
      evidence to a Verifier service for authentication.  The Verifier
      performs the following steps in sequence.</t>

      <t>First, the Verifier checks that every evidence record in the
      chain is properly signed by Bob's device key and that the
      signatures form a valid COSE_Sign1 chain.  Second, the Verifier
      recomputes each VDF output from its inputs and confirms that the
      chain is temporally consistent -- each VDF computation requires
      wall-clock time proportional to the configured difficulty
      parameter.  Third, the Verifier analyzes the keystroke timing
      data using statistical methods to confirm that the typing
      patterns are consistent with human authorship rather than
      automated generation.</t>

      <t>The Verifier produces an attestation result indicating that
      Bob's evidence chain is authentic with a confidence score of
      0.97.  Carol can present this attestation to publishers as
      evidence that the manuscript was genuinely authored by a human
      over the claimed time period.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The examples in this document use simplified and truncated
      values that are not suitable for production use.  Implementers
      MUST use full-length cryptographic values as specified in the
      base Proof of Process document.  The simplified values are
      provided solely to illustrate the protocol flow.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document has no IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC8174;
      &I-D.condrey-rats-pop;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC8949;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
