<section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations">

  <t>The security of the Proof of Process framework depends on several
  assumptions about the Attester's operating environment and the
  cryptographic primitives employed.</t>

  <section anchor="sec-security-attester" title="Attester Compromise">
    <t>If the Attester's device key is compromised, an adversary can
    forge evidence packets. Mitigations include:</t>
    <t>
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Hardware-bound keys stored in a TPM or Secure Enclave.</t>
        <t>Key rotation with forward secrecy for evidence chains.</t>
        <t>Device attestation certificates issued by the platform
        vendor.</t>
      </list>
    </t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec-security-replay" title="Replay Attacks">
    <t>An adversary may attempt to replay previously captured evidence
    packets. The VDF time-binding and session nonces prevent replay
    across sessions. Within-session replay is mitigated by the
    monotonic sequence numbers in each evidence packet and the
    chain hash linking consecutive packets.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec-security-entropy" title="Entropy Manipulation">
    <t>An adversary may attempt to generate synthetic behavioral data
    that passes entropy checks. The framework mitigates this through
    multi-dimensional entropy analysis across timing, revision patterns,
    and pause distributions. A successful attack requires simultaneous
    forgery across all dimensions, which is computationally bounded
    by the forgery cost model in <xref target="sec-forgery"/>.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="sec-security-relay" title="Relay Attacks">
    <t>A relay attack involves an adversary capturing evidence from
    a legitimate authorship session and presenting it as evidence for
    a different document. Content binding (the cryptographic hash of
    document state at each evidence window) prevents this attack, as
    the evidence is tied to specific content transitions.</t>
  </section>

</section>
